Hi בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ע"ה, daf
ayin hey, בבא קמא Bava Kamma 75, and we pick up about
ten lines down on ע"ה ayin hey .. and we're in the
middle of a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel whether when
a person admits to a קנס knas whether that actually exempts them
even if witnesses come after that an admission gets you a total
exemption. One way of thinking about that is a קנס knas is
a penalty because of the bad things that you did. So if
you come clean, then maybe you're not deserving of the penalty or
maybe we're trying to get you to come clean.
Whatever the explanation is, the קנס knas is an exemption that's רב's
Rav position. מודה בקנס אחר כך באו עדים פטור. Modeh b'knas achar
kach ba'u edim patur. And שמואל's Shmuel position is no. Excuse me,
not קנס knas is an exemption, הודאה hoda'ah is an exemption. When
you admit to doing it, that gives you an exemption even if
witnesses come after. That's רב's Rav position and שמואל's Shmuel position is
no, הודאה hoda'ah just doesn't obligate you but it does not exempt
you. מודה בקנס אחר כך באו עדים חייב Modeh b'knas achar kach
ba'u edim chayav if witnesses come afterwards. So now we're going to
continue with that debate. At the about ten lines down on ע"ה
ayin hey .. איתמר: Itmar: מודה בקנס אחר כך באו עדים, Modeh
b'knas achar kach ba'u edim, if you admitted to a קנס knas
and then witnesses came: רב אמר פטור, Rav amar patur, you're exempt
even though the witnesses now have the evidence. Your admission exempts you.
ושמואל אמר חייב. u'Shmuel amar chayav. No, your admission didn't obligate you,
and that's the difference again we should say from קנס knas from
ממון. mamon. If I say I borrowed a hundred dollars, that obligates
me. But קנס knas is something that is imposed by בית דין,
Beis Din, so it's not admitting to an existing obligation. It's admitting
to an act, but בית דין Beis Din has to impose the
obligation. So admission does not obligate you, but it also does not
give you an exemption. אמר רבה בר אילאי: Amar Rabbah bar Ilai:
מאי טעמא דרב? Mai ta'ama de'Rav? What's the reason of רב? Rav?
I'm going to say it's based on a
פסוק: pasuk: אם המצא תמצא. Im himatzei timatzei. So this is a
פסוק pasuk by somebody who claims טוען טענת גנב, to'en ta'anas gannav,
somebody who is watching an object and he claims that it was
stolen or actually burglarized and he's found lying. So then you treat
him like a גנב gannav and he pays כפל. kefel. אם המצא
תמצא בידו הגניבה משור עד חמור עד שה לחיים שנים ישלם.
Im himatzei timatzei beyado hagniva mishor
ad chamor ad seh lachayim shnayim yishalem. If it's found in his
hand, he has to pay כפל. kefel. So that's how we know
the idea about כפל kefel and we're also going to learn from
this פסוק pasuk that if not his own admission, it's only again
this קנס knas of כפל kefel is only through עדים. edim. אם
המצא: Im himatzei: if it is found in his hands, בעדים, be'edim,
meaning he didn't admit it but it was discovered through witnesses. תמצא
ביד הדיינים: Timatzei beyad hadayanim: if the witnesses identified that he stole
it, then the דיינים dayanim make him pay כפל. kefel. But on
his own admission, they can't make him pay כפל. kefel. פרט למודה
בעצמו: Prat le'modeh b'atzmo: that excludes a case of your own admission
will not lead to an obligation of קנס. knas. So now רבה
בר אילאי Rabbah bar Ilai says: למה לי? Lama li? Why do
I need a פסוק pasuk to exempt you for קנס knas by
your own admission? מאשר ירשיעון נפקא? Me'asher yarshi'un nafka? The פסוק pasuk
that says those that the judges, אשר ירשיעון אלהים ישלם שנים לרעהו.
Asher yarshi'un elohim yishalem shnayim lerei'ehu. It has to be imposed by
the judges. קנס knas is something that requires an imposition by the
judges and being found to be a רשע rasha and that's through
other people testifying against you. So why do we need it to
say it twice? אלא שמע מינה מודה בקנס אחר כך באו עדים
פטור. Ella shema mina modeh b'knas achar kach ba'u edim patur. You
need it twice: once tells you your own admission doesn't obligate you
and the second time tells you your own admission actually exempts you.
ושמואל אמר לך: u'Shmuel amar lach: no, I think that it does
not exempt you. Why does it have to tell me twice this
idea that your admission doesn't obligate you?
ההוא מיבעי ליה לגופו דעצמו Ha hu miba'ei lei legufo d'atzmo because
the פסוק pasuk is talking about טוען טענת גנב, to'en ta'anas gannav,
somebody who was a שומר shomer watched an object and claimed it
was burglarized. But how do I know that the same הלכה halacha
applies to the גנב? gannav? Maybe the תורה Torah is stricter by
a גנב gannav and even if you admit you're going to you
can obligate yourself? So it says it twice the idea that your
admission doesn't obligate you: one for טוען טענת גנב, to'en ta'anas gannav,
one for an actual גנב. gannav. But we do not learn from
that that it actually exempts you. And that's תנא דבי חזקיהו, Tanna
de'bei Chizkiyahu, that's what we learned earlier in the name of ביה
רב. Beih Rav. Okay, so you can't prove it from the פסוק.
pasuk. איתיביה רב לשמואל. Eiseiv Rav l'Shmuel. Rav asked Shmuel the following
based on the following: ראה עדים שממשמשין ובאין. Ra'ah edim she'memashmeshim u'va'in.
We got a ברייתא. braisa. Somebody saw the witnesses that were getting
ready to come to court. You know, so the guy actually saw
the witnesses hailing a taxi: take us to the courthouse,
and they were going to come testify that this guy, and he
knew they were going to testify that he had burglarized this item.
ואמר: Ve'amar: so he beats them to court and he says: גנבתי!
Ganavti! I admit it, I was a גנב. gannav. אבל לא טבחתי
ולא מכרתי, Aval lo tavachti ve'lo macharti, but I did not actually
do טביחה ומכירה, t'viacha u'mechira, but I do admit that I was
a גנב. gannav. And then the witnesses come and they actually say
he was a גנב gannav and he did טביחה ומכירה. t'viacha u'mechira.
So אינו משלם אלא קרן. eino meshalem ella keren. You only pay
the קרן, keren, the principal. Why? Actually, he beat them to the
court and he says, גנבתי, ganavti, I admit it, I was a
גנב, ganav, דלא טבחי ודלא מכרתי, d'lo tavchi v'lo macharti, but I
did not actually do טביחה ומכירה, tivcha umachira, but I do admit
that I was a גנב. ganav. And then the witnesses come and
they actually say he was a גנב ganav and he did טביחה
ומכירה. tivcha umachira. So אינו משלם אלא קרן. eino meshalem ela keren.
You only pay the principal. Why? Because since he did מודה בקנס
modeh b'knas out of court, even though he denied the טביחה ומכירה
tivcha umachira and the witnesses testify to that, but once you're not
going to pay כפל, kefel, you can't pay the four and five
because the removing the extra כפל kefel payment from it would not
get down to three and four and the Torah only obligates four
and five. That's the חידוש chiddush of the ברייתא braita that once
he got himself out of the extra כפל kefel payment, then even
though there's testimony against him and there was no admission by טביחה
ומכירה, tivcha umachira, he's still going to get off. But the question
is, okay, or the proof is, it sounds like the witnesses came
and testified to the טביחה ומכירה tivcha umachira and still his admission
gets him off. That seems to be a direct proof to רב
Rav that מודה בקנס פטור אף על פי שבאו עדים.
modeh b'knas patur af al pi
sheba'u eidim. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so שמואל Shmuel says back
to him, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שחזו עדים מאחוריו. hacha b'mai askinan
k'gon shechazu eidim me'achorav. He says, no, no, no, no, no, the
case here is that because he beat them to the court, they
took the taxi back. Ah, forget it, you already admitted. And then
they didn't come and testify against him. So actually the case is
not a case that the witnesses testified but because he admitted he
gets off; the case was because he admitted the witnesses didn't bother
to testify. Now obviously that does not sound like that at all,
but that's how he's claiming it and nevertheless there's a חידוש chiddush
because other witnesses say טביחה ומכירה tivcha umachira but once he got
himself off כפל, kefel, טביחה ומכירה tivcha umachira doesn't mean anything. Okay,
but no, it is not a case that the witnesses of the
גניבה gneiva came and that's why he doesn't pay כפל, kefel, not
because he's exempt but because nobody was מחייב mechayev him in כפל,
kefel, שחזו עדים מאחוריו. shechazu eidim me'achorav. So the גמרא Gemara does
not like that. והא מדקתני סיפא, v'ha midekatani seifa, the end of
the ברייתא braita teaches, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi
Shimon omer, that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says,
יבואו עדים ויעידו. yavo'u eidim v'ya'idu.
He says on that case, even though the guy came and beat
them to בית דין beis din and said I did it, he
says who cares, let the witnesses come and they'll be מחייב mechayev
him כפל kefel even with his admission. Okay, so that's what רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says. So it sounds like
the תנא קמא tana kama would say it won't help. So מכלל,
michlal, that suggests the תנא קמא סבר לא, tana kama savar lo,
the תנא קמא סבר
לא, tana kama savar lo, that the תנא קמא tana kama says
no, it won't help with the witnesses, once he admitted the witnesses
won't help. And רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says,
no, the witnesses will help. So it sounds very much that the
תנא קמא tana kama says מודה בקנס פטור modeh b'knas patur and
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon is saying חייב chayav
and they're debating whether the witnesses should bother to come or not.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so שמואל Shmuel says back to you,
לדידי כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון דקאי כוותי. l'didi k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon
d'ka'i k'vasi. Okay, I acknowledge it. The תנא קמא tana kama who
says don't bother coming, he holds that the מודה בקנס modeh b'knas
is an exemption that
witnesses can't obligate. But at least I have רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון.
Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. I'm fine with רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says
even with your admission, let the witnesses come and they'll obligate him.
And even for רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון... Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon... fine.
So שמואל Shmuel says it's a debate of תנאים, tana'im, that's the
way I like it. ולשמואל ודאי תנאי היא. u'l'Shmuel vadai tana'i hi.
So for שמואל Shmuel it's definitely a מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tana'im because
the תנא קמא tana kama says there's no point in coming, but
he's got רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar to back him up. לרב מי
לימא תנאי היא? l'Rav mi leima tana'i hi?
Is it clear that it's a debate of תנאים tana'im according to
רב? Rav? It seems like it's a debate of תנאים, tana'im, but
the גמרא's Gemara asking the question because there's a way to explain
that רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon is only saying
it in this particular case. Let's see. אמר לך רב, amar lach
Rav, רב Rav would say to you, אנא דאמרי אפילו כרבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון. ana d'amri afilu k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. I could say
even רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon agrees to me
that in general מודה בקנס modeh b'knas is an exemption and the
witnesses will not be able to obligate you. So why here does
he say the witnesses should come forward? עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון התם, ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon
hatam, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon only says it
in that case that the witnesses, it'll pay for them to come
forward, אלא משום דקא מודי מחמת ביסוסא דעדים. ela mishum d'ka modi
machmat bisusa d'eidim.
That was not a real הודאה. hoda'ah. That was an admission that
was prompted to beat the עדים eidim to court, not because he
really wanted to come clean. He only wanted to get himself out
of כפל. kefel. And that's why he beat them to court. Actually,
if you think about it, the scenario that he saw the witnesses
and he wanted to jump ahead and admit only makes sense that
the admission comes with an exemption, or maybe he just wanted to
feel like a good guy, okay, so maybe there's other ways to
explain. But anyway he says, listen, normally your admission will be an
exemption when it's a sincere admission, when it's a real הודאה, hoda'ah,
when it's something that you are doing because you want to come
clean. Okay, that's what exempts you. But if you are doing it
only for the to achieve the פטור ptur of כפל kefel and
not because you want to come clean, okay, then that actually is
not a הודאה. hoda'ah. I'll obligate you. You can't obligate yourself with
קנס, knas, but it won't exempt you either.
עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון התם אלא משום דקא
מודי מחמת ביסוסא דעדים. ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon
hatam ela mishum d'ka modi machmat bisusa d'eidim. In that case that
he's testifying
because he's afraid of
the עדים, eidim, that's not a real הודאה. hoda'ah. ...obligate you, it
gives you an exemption. רבי אלעזר בן שמעון *Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon*
says
that's not a real admission, okay, and it doesn't give you an
exemption. אבל הכא *aval hacha*, but in a normal case where you
didn't see the witnesses coming to court, and you just came forward
on your
own דמודי מאנפשיה *demodei me'anfsheih*, you're admitting because of your own prompting,
אפילו רבי אלעזר בן שמעון מודה *afilu Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon modeh*,
even רבי אלעזר בן שמעון *Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon* would say that
your admission gives you an exemption. Okay, so רב Rav, *Rav* could
say, I could say, everybody says your admission is an exemption, and
there's a debate when the admission is prompted because you're afraid that
the עדים edim. *edim* are going to come. But for שמואל Shmuel
*Shmuel*, it's clear that he has to say the חכמים *chachamim* disagree
with him, the חכמים *chachamim* who say even in that case when
you testified out of fear, there's no point in the עדים edim.
*edim* coming because your admission was an exemption. So שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*
has to acknowledge that there is the חכמים *chachamim* that disagree with
him. Okay, now, now we're going to see that maybe qualifying this
debate, or this idea of an exemption. אמר רב Rav, המנונא *Amar
Rav Hamnuna*, said רב Rav המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*, מסתברא מילתא דרב באומר
גנבתי ובאו עדים שגנב פטור ganavti v'ba'u edim she-ganav patur. דחייב עצמו
בקרן *mistabra milta deRav be'omer ganavti u'va'u edim sheganav patur dechayev atzmo
bekeren*. רב's Rav *Rav's* idea that admission could be an exemption is
a hard idea to swallow, so one of the things we first
put forward is maybe it have to be prompted by yourself. But
the other thing is when you really are obligating yourself for something,
part of what makes it a real admission, or if you want
to see it in a sort of instrumental way, part of what
will give you the right to get an exemption, one of the
reasons it will incent you to admit is if at least that
will get you to pay the principal. So when you say גנבתי
ganavti *ganavti*, because with your גנבתי *ganavti*, yes, it normally comes with
כפל kefal, *keifel*, but you're also admitting to a principal, that's a
real admission, again either because conceptually an admission means that you're obligating
yourself for something, you really are bringing some type of obligation on
you, you're losing something from it, that's a real admission, or because
you earn an exemption because,
or we'll give you an exemption in order to get you to
at least restore the principal to create an incentive. That makes sense.
שגנב פטור דחייב עצמו בקרן *sheganav patur dechayev atzmo bekeren*, obligating yourself
from the קרן keren. *keren*, that's when you get an exemption even
if witnesses come. אבל אמר לא גנבתי ובאו עדים edim שגנב *aval
amar lo ganavti u'va'u edim sheganav*, but if he denied being a
גנב *ganav*, and then the witnesses came that he did steal, and
then he said, okay fine, you proved me that I stole, by
the way I want to admit that I also did טביחה ומכירה
tvi'acha u'mechira *tevichah u'mechira*, not because he saw witnesses were about to
come, but now he just admitted it. Okay, maybe he wasn't even
trying to preempt witnesses, nevertheless he says in that case דחזר ואמר
טבחתי ומכרתי tavachti u'macharti, ובאו עדים edim שטבח ומכר *dechazar ve'amar tavachti
umacharti u'va'u edim shetavach umachar*, and the witnesses do come and say
that he did טביחה ומכירה tvi'acha u'mechira, *tevichah u'mechira*, in that case
חייב chayav. *chayav*. Your admission even if it was sincerely motivated is
not going to be an exemption, because the admission to טביחה ומכירה
tvi'acha u'mechira *tevichah u'mechira* once there's already evidence of גניבה gneiva *geneivah*,
you are not obligating yourself with anything. You are just getting yourself
off the hook. There's no obligation of ממון *mamon* there, it's all
קנס knas. *knas*, opposed to כפל kefal, *keifel* which is ממון *mamon*
plus קנס knas, *knas*, the principal is ממון *mamon*. Here that it's
all קנס *knas*, your admission is not getting you off the
hook—excuse me, your admission is only getting you off the hook and
even if it's sincerely motivated, that's not an admission. Admission has to
come with obligating yourself for something, דפטר נפשיה מכולא *depatar nafsheih mikula*,
okay, that he is in that case fully exempting himself and there
is nothing that he is obligating himself. That is not prompting that
earns you an exemption. Okay, so we've had a debate whether you
get your exemption according to רב Rav *Rav* with a debate of
תנאי *Tannaim* maybe, if you're being motivated to beat the עדים *edim*
to it, and now a different debate, not necessarily about motive, but
is it considered an exemption or a different claim that it wouldn't
be considered worthy of an exemption for רב Rav *Rav* if you
didn't obligate yourself in some principal. So, that's the claim of רב
Rav המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, said רבא *Rava*,
קפחינהו סבי דבי רב Rav *kapcheinhu sabei dbei Rav*, I have shown
up the elders of the house of רב *Rav* meaning רב המנונא
*Rav Hamnuna* and he's making this claim about רב's *Rav's* position, דהא
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *deha Rabban Gamliel*, because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
*Rabban Gamliel*, פוטר עצמו מכולה הוה *poter atzmo mikula havah*,
yesterday's דף daf *daf* whenever רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* said oh I
blinded the eye of טבי Tavi *Tavi* my servant, and we had
a whole discussion whether that
admission exempted him or just didn't obligate him. And when somebody actually
the קנס *knas* of an עבד *eved*, if somebody says I blinded
the eye, he's not obligating himself in anything, that's all קנס *knas*.
The freeing of the עבד *eved* is all conceived of as קנס
*knas*, there's no principal, there's no ממון *mamon* that that admission obligates
you in. It also requires עדים *edim* and it's also קנס *knas*.
So in that case... רבן גמליאל פוטר עצמו מכולם הוי, in that
case he was exempting himself from everything, there was nothing he was
obligating himself in, it was all קנס. ורמי ליה רב חסדא לרב
הונא, v'rami leh Rav Chisda le-Rav Huna, and רב חסדא Rav Chisda
challenged רב הונא Rav Huna and he said, you see, this sounds
like if witnesses were going to come because he said it doesn't
matter because there's already עדים. And that was used as a proof
that if, because, excuse me, because there aren't עדים. So that discussion
with רבן גמליאל there and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was used as
a proof that were there עדים you would be חייב. chayav, Remember
that was the proof. And then there was also, why, you see,
admission isn't an exemption because it sounds like if there were עדים
you'd be חייב, chayav and he says it was outside of a
בית דין, beit din, it wasn't an admission because it wasn't in
the presence of a בית דין, beit din, etc. So he says,
there was a better answer, according to you רב הונא. Rav Huna.
He
says ולא קמשני ליה, v'lo ka meshani leh, and why didn't it
give your answer רב הונא? Rav Huna? Why didn't he say, okay,
in that case he did not earn you an exemption, forget in
בית דין beit din or out of בית דין, beit din, because
you weren't obligating yourself in a principle. So since that text of
רבן גמליאל and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and about טבי Tavi his
servant and so on was all in a whole discussion about whether
your admission exempts you or just doesn't obligate you, it sounds like
the principle of רב, because they were debating the position of רב,
that רב's position is, does not matter whether you're obligating yourself in
some principle or not, that רב's position actually is even if you're
fully exempting yourself like the case of the servant, that could still
serve as an exemption. You do not need חיוב עצמו בקרן chiyuv
atzmo b'keren for your הודאה hoda'ah to be, to exempt you if
witnesses were to come later. Okay, איתמר
נמי,
itmar
nami, it was also taught, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, גנבתי ובאו עדים
שגנב פטור. If a guy says I stole and witnesses came, then
you're exempt. שהרי חיוב עצמו בקרן, she-harei chiyuv atzmo b'keren, because that's
a type of admission that's an exemption because you're at least obligating
yourself in a principle. לא גנבתי ובאו עדים שגנב ואחר כך אמר
טבחתי ומכרתי ובאו עדים שטבח ומכר חייב. lo ganavti v'ba'u edim she-ganav
v'achar kach amar tavachti u'macharti v'ba'u edim she-tavach u'machar chayav.
So if you said I didn't steal, then witnesses say that you
burgled and you did, witnesses say that you did, so okay, now
you're חייב chayav, כפל, and then you said טבחתי ומכרתי, I slaughtered
it or sold it, and then witnesses say that you slaughtered and
sold, so in that case of טביחה ומכירה tvi'acha u'mechira חייב, chayav.
that case if the witnesses come after you admitted to טביחה ומכירה,
tvi'acha u'mechira your admission won't give you an exemption. Why not? שהרי
פטר עצמו מכלום, she-harei patar atzmo mikolum, because in that case you
are exempting yourself from everything, you're not obligating yourself in anything, that
is not an admission that functions as an exemption. So even
though רבא said, from the way we discussed the case before about
טבי it sounds like רב doesn't distinguish, and maybe that's true, maybe
רב doesn't distinguish between whether you're obligating yourself in a principle or
not, but at least here we have a statement of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, this idea is a very live idea. The way to
sort of split the difference between רב and שמואל is to say
an admission that obligates you in principle, that will get an exemption,
an admission in the principle,
whatever, in the קרן. keren Anyway, whereas an admission that only exempts
you, that doesn't obligate you in anything, that only relates to a
קנס, that doesn't serve as an exemption. Okay, so that's רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan position even if it isn't רב's position, to distinguish between
a real admission that comes with an obligation, that's an exemption, and
one that doesn't come with an obligation, that does not warrant an
exemption. Okay, אמר רב אשי מתניתין וברייתא נמי דייקא, Amar Rav Ashi
matnitin u'braita nami dika, רב אשי Rav Ashi said
a מתניתין matnitin and a ברייתא braita we also by a close
textual reading can infer this difference between an admission with an obligation
and an admission that doesn't come with an obligation.
Okay, מתניתין, matnitin, our משנה, mishna, דתנן, ditnan, and going back to
what we said earlier, גנב על פי שנים וטבח על פי עד
אחד או על פי עצמו משלם תשלומי כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמשה. ganav al pi shnayim v'tavach al pi ad echad o al
pi atzmo meshaleim tashlumei kefal v'eino meshaleim tashlumei arba'a v'chamisha. If somebody
stole with two witnesses and then he slaughtered on the basis of
one witness or based on his own admission,
משלם תשלומי כפל meshaleim tashlumei kefal because there were witnesses but you
don't pay four and five, that was your admission. למה לי דתני
גנב על פי שנים? lamah li de-tani ganav al pi shnayim? Why
did it have to say give the case that the גניבה gneiva
was with witnesses and the טביחה ומכירה tivchah u'mechira was your own
admission? ליתני גנב וטבח על פי עד אחד או על פי עצמו
ומשלם את הקרן. letni ganav v'tavach al pi ad echad o al
pi atzmo u'meshaleim et ha-keren. Why didn't it give all the examples?
If you admitted to the גניבה gneiva? you're only going to pay
קרן keren and not כפל, if you admitted to the טביחה ומכירה
tivchah u'mechira, you're not going to pay four and five, why if
it was trying to say your admission doesn't obligate you or exempts
you, why did it only give the example by טביחה ומכירה tivchah
u'mechira. that your admission, why didn't it also talk about an admission
by the גניבה? geneivah אלא לאו הכי קא משמע לן, ela lav
haka ka mashma lan, and this is what it's teaching me, גנב
על פי שנים וטבח על פי עד אחד. ganav al pi shnayim
v'tavach al pi ad echad.
So it's in that case when it's where the word hu was
throwing me off, but the ב''ח ורש''י Bach ve-Rashi take out that
word. Let's read that again. אלא לאו הא קמשמע לן, Ela lav
ha kamashman, גנב על פי שנים וטבח על פי עד אחד או
על פי עצמו, gannav al pi shnayim u'tavach al pi ed echad
o al pi atzmo, in the case where there's witnesses to the
גניבה geneivah but the admission
for of טביחה ומכירה tivchah u'mechira is based on your own testimony
or one witness, דלא מחייב עצמו בקרן de-lo mechayev atzmo be-keren
and that's a case where your admission is not obligating yourself under
principal, that's the case that it's only on the טביחה ומכירה, tivchah
u'mechira, הוא דאמרינן על פי עצמו דומיא דעל פי עד אחד. hu
de-amrinan al pi atzmo dumya de-al pi ed echad. Remember this from
like two days ago or a day ago? That the גמרא Gemara
said that there's a דיוק diyuk that it sounds like your admission
is like the admission of an עד אחד ed echad because it
gave them as parallel cases in the משנה. mishna. What's the point?
Is that על פי עד אחד al pi ed echad clearly that's
not an exemption, it's just not an obligation, but if witnesses were
to come afterwards you would be obligated. So similarly the גמרא Gemara
said it sounds like from the משנה mishna that also your own
admission is not enough to obligate you, but it's not an exemption,
same way one witness is not an exemption, your own admission is
not an exemption and if witnesses were to come later it would
obligate you. Great, so we made a דיוק diyuk in the משנה,
mishna, this is a דיוק diyuk we made the other day, that
it sounds like your own admission does not obligate you but also
does not exempt you, just like עד אחד. ed echad. And now
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is: and that's why it only
spoke about it in the case of טביחה ומכירה. tivchah u'mechira Because
by טביחה ומכירה tivchah u'mechira where you're not מחייב עצמו בקרן, mechayev
atzmo be-keren, that's where we're teaching that your admission doesn't obligate but
also doesn't exempt. That's when על פי עצמו al pi atzmo is
similar to על פי עד אחד al pi ed echad when it's
about something that is not obligating yourself for anything. That's why you
don't get an exemption and if witnesses come after you'd be חייב.
chayav, But if it was about the גניבה geneivah where you do
obligate yourself in the קרן keren, then you even get the exemption.
Let's read that inside. דומיא דעל
פי עד אחד, dumya de-al pi ed echad, in the same way
when it's one witness, כי אתי עד מצטרף בהדיה ki atei ed
mitztaref bahadeih when another witness comes to join with him מחייב mechayev
you'd be חייב, chayav. so meaning על פי עד אחד al pi
ed echad doesn't obligate you but also doesn't give you an exemption.
So the implication in the משנה mishna is על פי עצמו נמי
al pi atzmo nami the same is true by your own admission,
כי אתו סהדי מחייב ki atu sahadei mechayev that your own admission
doesn't exempt you and if witnesses come you'd be חייב. That's the
implication in the משנה, mishna, that your own admission isn't an exemption.
And that's why the משנה mishna made a point of teaching it
only by טביחה ומכירה, tivchah u'mechira. because by טביחה ומכירה your admission
isn't an exemption because you're not obligating yourself in anything. אבל גנב
וטבח ומכר על פי עד אחד ועל פי עצמו, Aval gannav u'tavach
u'machar al pi ed echad ve-al pi atzmo, but if you actually
admitted to the גניבה by yourself, ומחייב עצמו בקרן u'mechayev atzmo be-keren
and in that case you are obligating yourself in the קרן, לא
אמרינן על פי עצמו דומיא דעל פי עד אחד, lo amrinan al
pi atzmo dumya de-al pi ed echad, we would not have said
that your own admission is like עד אחד, ed echad, we would
have said that in that case your own admission actually earns you
an exemption. So that's a very nice דיוק. diyuk. If you remember
when we first read the משנה, mishna, the גמרא Gemara first read
the משנה, mishna, it said it sounds like that the משנה mishna
is telling me because על פי עצמו דומיא דעל פי עד אחד,
al pi atzmo dumya de-al pi ed echad, it sounds like your
own admission does not earn you an exemption. And here the גמרא
Gemara is saying yes, it does sound like that, but that does
not mean שמואל, it actually means רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, because it
does not mean it never earns you an exemption, it means it
never earns you an exemption when you're admitting to טביחה ומכירה when
there's no, when you're not obligating yourself. That's why the משנה mishna
said it only by טביחה ומכירה. But if you said גנבתי and
you obligated yourself, then actually it would earn you an exemption. Okay,
so we're going to stop here even though there's a lot of
דף daf left to do, because if you haven't figured this out
yet, this is most of the דף daf, here is from seven
years ago, but now I'm also recording to make up the missing
דפים dappim for שבת, Shabbos, and the upcoming דף, if you take
a quick peek ahead in ע''ז Ayin-Zayin is extremely tiny, there's one
line of גמרא, Gemara, so we actually have the rest recorded, so
we will be covering the rest of ע''ה Ayin-Hei and ע''ו Ayin-Vov
tomorrow and then we'll be all caught up by the day after.
We're going to stop here and to be continued tomorrow.